All right. So, today we are building on
the previous video. So, the previous
video I talked about the many offlabel
benefits of testosterone
particularly in the in the sense that
testosterone replacement is beneficial
for people who have a compromised
metabolic health or people have
compromised metabolic health such as
those with fatty liver disease, insulin
resistance, high visceral atoposity,
diabetes, things that fall within that
scope. Now on the other side of the
spectrum today I'm going to talk about
how thyroid hormones can be beneficial
for those who also have compromised
metabolic health. There are numerous
mechanisms how thyroid hormone can have
a role in the development or even as a
possible supplemental treatment for
these various metabolic conditions. So
the first one I'll talk about is the
role of thyroid hormone with fatty liver
disease. In states of insulin resistance
there's this process called denovo
lipogenesis and its activity kind of
gets upregulated. So denovalogenesis is
essentially the process in which
carbohydrates are converted into fat.
Meanwhile, insulin resistance itself
suppresses lipolysis which is the
breakdown of fat. So you can kind of see
how this is a two-fold combo that leads
to the accumulation of fat within the
liver itself. Hypothyroidism also
suppresses LDLR activity. Well, LDLR are
the receptors within a liver that
dispose of LDLs. So that's another
third-way mechanism that can contribute
further more to fatty liver disease.
Another thing we know is that even in
mildly hypothyroid patients and this is
what the literature has told us in
mildly hypothyroid patients insulin
production from the pancreatic beta
cells can actually be reduced as well.
So you now have less insulin to break
down glucose. And since there's less
insulin being produced by the pancreatic
beta cells, that means there's less
insulin breaking down carbohydrates,
which means you now have more
carbohydrates available to participate
in denovo lipogenesis. And thus, it's
this insulin cycle. And as I said just a
moment ago, even mildly hypothyroid
patients can have a reduced production
of insulin. So with the introduction of
thyroid replacement therapy, we can
theoretically get their insulin
production back to a normal level. Also,
I mentioned that there's LDLR receptor
activity gets downregulated in
hypothyroid patients. So, theoretically,
we could reverse that and dispose of
lipids that way. And lastly, there's
also thyroid hormone receptors within
the liver itself. And many of these
receptors are capable of increasing
fatty acid oxidation. As I mentioned at
the beginning of this video, there's an
accumulation of fat as well as
triglycerides within the liver. By
upregulating these hormone receptors
within the liver, we can increase the
breakdown of these fats and
triglycerides.